<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The present state of the Morea, called anciently, Peloponnesus which hath been near two hundred years under the dominion of the Turks, and is now very much depopulated : together with a description of the city of Athens, islands of Zant, Strafades, and Serigo / faithfully described by Bernard Randolph, who resided in those parts from 1671 to 1679.</title>
            <author>Randolph, Bernard, b. 1643.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57948</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R235</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13431</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13019481</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13019481</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96620</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57948)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96620)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 398:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The present state of the Morea, called anciently, Peloponnesus which hath been near two hundred years under the dominion of the Turks, and is now very much depopulated : together with a description of the city of Athens, islands of Zant, Strafades, and Serigo / faithfully described by Bernard Randolph, who resided in those parts from 1671 to 1679.</title>
                  <author>Randolph, Bernard, b. 1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and are to be sold by Tho. Basset ... John Penn ... and John Hill ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"By His Majesties special licence"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Peloponnesus (Greece) --  Description and travel.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96620:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96620:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PRESENT STATE OF THE MOREA, Called Anciently Peloponneſus: Which hath been near Two Hundred Years under the Dominion of the <hi>Turks;</hi> and is now very much Depopulated.</p>
            <p>Together with a Deſcription of the City of <hi>ATHENS,</hi> Iſlands of <hi>ZANT, STRAFADES,</hi> and <hi>SERIGO.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Faithfully Deſcribed by <hi>BERNARD RANDOLPH,</hi> who reſided in thoſe parts from 1671 to 1679.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By His Majeſties Special Licence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, and are to be ſold by <hi>Tho. Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet, John Penn</hi> under the Arch in the <hi>Temple,</hi> and <hi>John Hill</hi> in <hi>Exchange-alley.</hi> 1686.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:96620:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96620:2"/>
            <head>MOREA, <hi>ſometime called</hi> PELOPONNESUS, <hi>and by the</hi> Turks MORA.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Iſthmus</hi> or <hi>Hexamile</hi> is a Neck of Land which joyneth it to the Continent of <hi>Greece,</hi> and makes it a <hi>Peninſula.</hi> The Length is about ten Miles, and the Breadth at the narroweſt place not above Six. There are the Ruines of Three Caſtles, and a Wall which reacht from the City of <hi>Canchrea</hi> on the <hi>Egean</hi> Sea, to <hi>Lechaeum</hi> on the Gulph of <hi>Lepanto.</hi> There is alſo a Valley where they endeavoured to have both Seas joyn'd.</p>
            <div type="location">
               <head>CORINTH, by the <hi>Turks</hi> GO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RDESE,</head>
               <p>Is an Ancient City which ſtands on a Riſing Ground, about Two Miles from the Sea of the Gulph of <hi>Lepanto.</hi> The Houſes are much ſcattered, having many Fields amongſt them, together with which they take up above three Miles in compaſs. There are many pleaſant Gardens with all ſorts of Fruits. The Houſes here are more for Trade and Pleaſure than Security, moſt having other Houſes up in the Caſtle, which ſtands upon a Hill. To this they retreat when any Pyrats come to annoy them, which is often in the Summer time; they coming with their <hi>Briganteens,</hi> to the <hi>Iſth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> which is not above ſix Miles off. The Hill on which the Caſtle ſtands is very high, it was formerly called the <hi>Acro Corinthus,</hi> and is very ſteep round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout; the part towards the Weſt, North and North
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96620:3"/>Eaſt being almoſt Perpendicular. It is above two Miles from the Town to the Caſtle. The way up is much winding, and alſo ſteep. The Hill is all Stone. The For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications are very Ancient. There are two Walls before you paſs into the chiefeſt part of the Caſtle. The Hill is Walled round at the Top, which is above three Miles. There are ſome Guns which are of no other uſe than to Salute any Great Perſon, or to fire on their Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals. From the Northermoſt part is one of the moſt pleaſant Proſpects the World affords, looking into the Gulph of <hi>Lepanto, Aegean</hi> Sea, and ſeveral Mountains at great diſtance, together with thoſe moſt pleaſant Plains of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and <hi>Baſilico,</hi> which abound with Olive-trees, Vine-yards, and many ſmall Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages. In the Caſtle the Land is good, where are many Paſture Fields, and plenty of Water, ſo as it may endure a long Siege; to the Weſt there is a Spring which guſheth out from the Top of the Hill, and fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth down above Fifty Fathome. In the Plains of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth</hi> were the firſt Currant Vines Planted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <head>VOSTIZA,</head>
               <p>Is about twenty Miles within the Mouth of the Gulph of <hi>Lepanto,</hi> Seated on a Riſing Ground about a Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a Mile from the Sea-ſide. It is but a ſmall Town without any Fortifications. The Plain about it affords Corn, Currants, and Wine, Olive-trees there are not many, it lying too open to the Norther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Winds, which bring very cold Blaſts from the Mountains on the other ſide the Gulph. The Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains to the South, are not above Five Miles from the Town, which are very high, and continue to the Plains of <hi>Baſilico,</hi> betwixt which and the Sea is the Road to <hi>Corinth,</hi> which is very bad way to paſs in the Winter, there being no cut Rivers, and the Floods over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96620:3"/>make ſeveral Waters, ſome above a Mile broad. There are no Inhabitants between the Plain of <hi>Baſilico</hi> and this Place, nor is the Soil good, being moſt Stony, and having many Woods, nor is it above two Miles from the Sea to the Mountains in moſt places. There is no Port at <hi>Voſtiza,</hi> nor any Shelter for Boats on all this ſide of the Gulph.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <head>PARTRASS, formerly called PATRA,</head>
               <p>Is an Ancient City. It ſtands about Nine Miles without the Caſtles, at the Mouth of the Gulph of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panto,</hi> on a Hill about a Quarter of a Mile from the Sea. The greateſt part of the Town runs down to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the South Eaſt, overlooking the Plain. The Houſes are thick, and are above two Miles about, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding the Caſtle, which ſtands to the North above the Town. The Caſtle is well built, having very high Walls, to the Eaſtward is a dry Ditch with a low Wall; towards the Sea is a round Tower well built, high and ſtrong, which has Six very long Guns to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Road, but they lye too high to do any harm to Ships, except a Shot ſhould chance to hit any of the Maſts. There are many Ruines about the City. To the Eaſtward is a very great Mountain, the Foot of which is about ten Miles from the Town. The Plain is very delightſome, having many pleaſant Gardens with all ſorts of Fruits. The largeſt, and beſt Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons are here of any place in the <hi>Morea:</hi> At the Sea ſide there are only a few Store-houſes. About a Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a Mile from them to the South, are the Ruines of a Great Church which was Dedicated to St. <hi>Andrew.</hi> There are no Fortifications by the Sea-ſide nearer than the Caſtles at the Gulph. In the Summer time there is a continual Watch by the Sea-ſide, of both Horſe and Foot; the Town dividing into ſeveral Parties, one
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96620:4"/>Party goes down every night ſcouting along the Marine, not ſuffering any Boats to come a ſhore till it be Day. Before this place was the great fight betwixt the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and the <hi>Turks,</hi> in <hi>October</hi> 1571. when the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were Victorious.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <head>GASTON, formerly called ELIS,</head>
               <p>Stands in a very large Plain about Eight Miles from the Bay of <hi>Chiarenza.</hi> The Houſes are very much ſcatter'd; without Walls or any Fortification. The greateſt part of the Inhabitants are Husbandmen. The Country about it is very pleaſant. There are ſeveral large Woods about it. The Land is moſt Plow'd, and Paſture Land, having very few Olive or Fruit trees. In the time of War with the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians,</hi> here is uſually a <hi>Baſſha</hi> with a Number of Horſe. who guard the Coaſt. There is no Fortification by the Sea-ſide from the Gulph of <hi>Lepanto</hi> to <hi>Navareene,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Caſtle of <hi>Arcadia</hi> a Mile from the Sea. From <hi>Partraſs</hi> to <hi>Gaſton</hi> the way is plain, and ſo continues to <hi>Navardene</hi> a long the Sea ſide. The Black Mountains, and Caſtle <hi>Torneſe</hi> are left on the Leſt hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <head>Caſtle TORNESE, by the <hi>Turks</hi> called CLOM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TCH,</head>
               <p>Stands on a high Hill on a Promontory, the moſt Weſt of all the <hi>Morea.</hi> It is about Six Miles from the Ruines of <hi>Chiarenza,</hi> and not above Eighteen Miles from the Iſland of <hi>Zante.</hi> At Sea it ſeems to be an Iſland. The Caſtle is well built, having the Walls very high, but much out of repair. It has no Ditch about it, nor has it any other Strength than from the Scituation, not having above twenty Guns. Under the Walls is a ſmall Town where Sir <hi>Henry Hide</hi> (who was ſometime Conſul for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation in the <hi>Morea</hi>) lived in great State, built a ſmall Church, and a fair Houſe with many Gardens and Vine-yards
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96620:4"/>about it. The Church remains entire. The Scituation is very pleaſant, and was by the <hi>Venetians</hi> called <hi>Bel videre.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <head>ARCADIA, formerly called CYPARISSA,</head>
               <p>Stands in a Great Bay about a Mile from the Sea. The Caſtle and Town ſtand on ſcragged Rocks, under high Mountains. The Caſtle is much out of repair, nor can it be made ſtrong to reſiſt any Enemy, the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains ſo overlooking it. Before it is a pleaſant Plain along the Sea ſide. It has no Harbour for Shipping, ſo that they carry their Oyl and other Merchandize to <hi>Navareene.</hi> In time of Peace with the <hi>Venetians,</hi> they carry them to <hi>Zante.</hi> The Town is ſmall and not much inhabited.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <head>NAVAREENE, formerly called PYL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</head>
               <p>Has the beſt Harbour in all the <hi>Morea.</hi> It is about five Miles long, and three broad, having an Iſland ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before it called <hi>Spactoria.</hi> Formerly there where two Entrances into the Harbour, but in the Year 1571, when the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> obtained the great Victory over the <hi>Turks</hi> before the Gulph of <hi>Lepanto;</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſeveral Ships, and Gallies in the Harbour, and fearing the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> would come in and deſtroy them, ſtopped up the Entrance to the Weſt of the Iſland (ſo as only ſmall Boats can now paſs;) and built a very ſtrong Caſtle to the Eaſtward called New <hi>Navareene,</hi> which is very well built, and commands the Entrance. It has about Forty Guns, which are moſt towards the Sea. The Land to the South Eaſt lies high. To the weſt end of the Harbour ſtands Old <hi>Navareene</hi> (formerly called <hi>Pylus</hi>) on a high Hill very ſteep; the Walls are very much out of repair, great part
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96620:5"/>being fallen down, there are very few Inhabitants in it. It might be made impregnable, no hills being near it. I cannot ſay whether they have any Guns in it. This place in other Maps is put down above 20 Miles from the Sea, and the Iſland of <hi>Spactoria</hi> (which makes the Harbour) left out.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <head>MODON,</head>
               <p>Is a very ſtrong Caſtle which ſtands on a low Point of Land. The Sea waſheth the Foundations of the Walls above three Quarters round: the Walls are very high. The Port is to the Eaſtward, it hath a ſmall Mole to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain two or three Gallies; the Port is not ſecure for Ships, South Weſt Winds having too great Power here. To the South lies the Iſland of <hi>Sapienza</hi> about two Miles from the Point of the Caſtle. To command the Paſſage a round Tower is built, which hath ſeveral great Guns, that lye equal with the Water. Towards the Land by the Port is a dry Ditch five Yards deep, and about twenty Yards broad, between which and the main Caſtle is a very ſtrong Battery of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ten Guns. There is a dry Ditch, and Draw-bridges to paſs into the Body of the Caſtle. To the North Weſt is another Battery to ſecure that Mount, where are very good Guns. On the Walls towards the Port are three Towers, in each of which are ſmall Guns: in all, they ſay, here are about One hundred Guns. The Town ſtands about half a Mile from the Caſtle, being inhabited by <hi>Greeks.</hi> In the Port is a ſmall Iſland on which a Battery might be raiſed and do much harm to the Caſtle, it being as high as the Walls. The Caſtle is above a Mile about.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <head>CORON,</head>
               <p>Is ſcituated on a Point of Land which runs out about half a Mile. It is much higher towards the Land then
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96620:5"/>at the Point. The Sea goes two Thirds about it. The Walls are high, and their Foundations on ſcraggy Rocks. The Fortification is in much better repair than at <hi>Modon.</hi> Towards the Land the Walls are above Forty Foot high, and here is a round Tower above Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Foot high, in which are ſeveral very good Guns to anſwer the Land, which runs higher than the Walls. At the Southward part of the Caſtle the Land goes ſloping down towards the Sea ſide, from the Walls of the Caſtle, the ground is not Rocky in that part. There are about ſeventy good Guns about the Wall, and ſeveral of the Works are Arch'd over. To the North is a round Tower which ſtands low to command the Road. Here is no Harbour for Gallies, nor is the Road very ſecure. It had formerly a good Mole which is now ſunk; which, with other Ruines has ſo choak'd up the harbour, that moſt buoy up their Cables with Cask to keep them from ground.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <head>CALAMATA, formerly called TH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M,</head>
               <p>Is at the bottom of the Bay of <hi>Coron,</hi> about a Mile from the Sea. The Caſtle is but ſmall. The Town is near a Mile in Circumference, well Peopled, ſtanding on a riſing Ground. To the Weſt is a very large and fertile Plain, in which are many <hi>Greek</hi> Villages, and two ſmall Towns, the one called <hi>Cochiuk Magna,</hi> the other <hi>Niſcia.</hi> The latter is moſt ſmall Iſlands, which little Rivers make. (<hi>Niſcia</hi> ſignifying Iſlands in the Vulgar <hi>Greek.</hi>) The Plain about <hi>Calamata</hi> towards the Sea is all planted with Vineyards, Olive, Figg and Mulberry-trees. On the Weſt part of the Bay by the Sea ſide, are the Ruines of Old <hi>Meſſina,</hi> which the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> beſieged with a powerful Army. The <hi>Meſſineſes</hi> ſeeing they were not able to withſtand their Enemies Power, fired their City, imbarked themſelves, and went to <hi>Sicilia,</hi> where they built the preſent City of <hi>Meſſina.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96620:6"/>
               <head>MESITHA, formerly called LACEDEMON,</head>
               <p>Is ſcituated at the ſide of a large Plain on a riſing Ground, about twenty five Miles from the Sea ſide, having very high Mountains all to the Weſt of the Plain. The Caſtle ſtands to the Weſt on a very high Hill, ſteep on the Weſt, and South part, where it is inac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſable, but ſloping to the North, having two old Walls which croſs the Hill from the North to the South, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding the Hill almoſt into three Parts. The way into the Caſtle is very difficult. The Walls of the Caſtle are well built, but very old. It is near half a Mile about, having two Gates to be paſs'd. The Town is large, and is eſteemed the ſecond for bigneſs in all the <hi>Morea,</hi> yet <hi>Patraſs</hi> hath more houſes. The Ruines about it are very great, and towards the South they reach above four Miles, having in ſome places the Foundation of a thick Wall, which they ſay was the Walls of <hi>Sparta.</hi> To the North about a Quarter of a Mile from the Town, is a great and high Building, which they ſay was an Arch of an Aquaeduct. The Plain is very pleaſant, full of ſmall Villages, Olive, and Mulberry trees. This Place and <hi>Calamata</hi> make more Silk than all the other parts of the <hi>Morea.</hi> The River which runs through the Plain is now called <hi>Vaſili Pottamo.</hi> In Winter it ſpreads very large, but in Summer towards the City is almoſt dry. Tho' the City ſtands remote from the Sea, and free from dangers that enſue from thence; yet the <hi>Manjotts</hi> are a People apt to prey upon them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <head>MAINA, which ſome write BRAZZO di MAINA,</head>
               <p>Is that Country where the <hi>Manjotts</hi> inhabit. It lies Weſt of the Plain of <hi>Miſitha,</hi> and ſo runs down to the Sea, being Mountanous and full of Woods, and very
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96620:6"/>difficult to come at, either by Sea, or Land. In the Year 1667, they rebelled and ſent to the <hi>Venetians</hi> and <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſes</hi> who came to their aſſiſtance, bringing with them Powder, and other Ammunition. Many Parties of them would often make Incurſions into the <hi>Turks</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and did much harm. But the Captain <hi>Baſſha,</hi> who went with Forty Gallies, to relieve a Caſtle called <hi>Zarnata,</hi> reduced them to their former Obedience. Articles were drawn up, in which the <hi>Manjotts</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to pay a ſmall Tribute. Yet do they continue to cruiſe about with their <hi>Briganteens.</hi> If they take any <hi>Turks,</hi> they ſell them to the <hi>Malteſes,</hi> and <hi>Legor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſes,</hi> as they do the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to the <hi>Turks.</hi> If any Ship come to Anchor on their Coaſt, many arm them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and go to the place, over againſt where the Ship doth ride; ſome of them will be in Prieſts Habits, walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Sea ſide, with their Wallets, in which they will have ſome Wine and Bread. Their Companions lye hid behind the Buſhes at ſome convenient Poſt. When any ſtrangers come aſhore, who do not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand their Language, the feigned Prieſts make ſigns to them, ſhewing them their Bread and Wine, which they offer to them for money, by which the ſtrangers being enticed from the Sea fide (and it may be to ſit down and taſt their Wine) the hidden <hi>Manjotts</hi> come and make their Prey. The Prieſts will ſeem to be ſorry, and endeavour to make the ſtrangers believe they were altogether ignorant of any ſuch deſign. So a white Flagg is put out, and a Treaty held with the Ship for their Ranſome. The Prieſts endeavour to moderate the Price, ſhewing a great deal of reſpect to their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, who are cloathed in <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Habits. Many Ships have been thus ſerved. Such a buſineſs happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships, who (having the Winds con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary) came to Anchor near the Iſland <hi>Cervi,</hi> (in one of which Sir <hi>Paul Rycaut</hi> was a Paſſenger going for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96620:7"/>
                  <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi>) ſeveral Young Men were taken, and they paid dear for viſiting the <hi>Manjotts,</hi> and though the Earl of <hi>Winchilſea,</hi> (then Embaſſadour (from his Majeſty) at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi>) made complaint of it, no redreſs could be had. In the Plains are many Olive Trees, and Vine-yards: In the Woods there are many wild Vines. There are great quantities of Quailes, ſo as they Salt them up, and ſend them to ſeveral other parts. Powder and Shot is here ſcarce, but they do ſo well manage the Sling, as is to admiration, with which they kill Birds on the Wing. The Sea Ports in <hi>Maina,</hi> are, <hi>Chetri, Vitulo, Porto Quaglio, Yaracaria, Pagana, Rapana,</hi> with ſeveral other ſmall Ports and Creeks, where they ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter themſelves when they are purſued. The Garriſons which the <hi>Turks</hi> have in <hi>Maine</hi> are <hi>Zarnata, Vitulo, Kifala,</hi> and <hi>Paſſava.</hi> Here are two Famous Pyrats, the one called <hi>Manetta,</hi> the other <hi>Giracare,</hi> being the chief for Family and Power amongſt them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <head>MAL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ASIA, formerly called EPIDA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RES,</head>
               <p>Is a ſtrong Caſtle ſtanding on a Rock about twenty Miles to the North of the Cape St. <hi>Anzolo</hi> in the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chipelago.</hi> It has a narrow and difficult Paſſage to the Continent. It is very well Fortified with good Works, having about 100 good Guns; notwithſtanding it ſtands in the Sea, and ſeems to be all Rock, yet it hath on the top a fine Plain with Gardens and ſeveral Springs, with good Water. This place ſtands very convenient for tranſporting Men and Proviſion for <hi>Candy,</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing above thirty Leagues diſtance from <hi>Canea:</hi> Hence the Viſier <hi>Kupri-Ogle</hi> ſailed when he went for <hi>Candy,</hi> and more Souldiers were Shipped from hence for <hi>Candy</hi> (in the late War) than from any other Port of <hi>Turky.</hi> It is very populous, and the Seamen are eſteemed the beſt of any in theſe parts. Here are the choiceſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96620:7"/>Wines, eſteemed at <hi>Venice</hi> to be the beſt of all in <hi>Greece.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <head>NAPOLI,</head>
               <p>Is a large City, now the chief in all the <hi>Morea,</hi> being above two Miles in Compaſs, the Sea going almoſt round it. The houſes ſtand thick, and very full of People. It is the Seat of the <hi>Baſſha.</hi> The Caſtle is well ſeated to the North, ſtanding above any part of the Town. There is but one way into the City by Land, which is at the ſide of high Mountains, very difficult. The Harbour is very ſecure, having a narrow entrance, paſſing Rocks ſo as but one Gally can come in at a time. Before which Entrance is a Fort built on low Rocks, where are ſeveral very good Guns. It ſtands about 300 Paces from the Haven, have ſhoal Water round about it. No Ships can come to hurt the City with their Shot, it being cover'd to Seaward from any danger, by high and ſtrong Walls, on which and in the Caſtles are above 200 Guns.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <head>ARGOS,</head>
               <p>Is about twenty four Miles from the Sea. It ſtands in a very fine Plain, having more Houſes and Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants than <hi>Corinth,</hi> but not ſo much ſcattered. The Caſtle is ſeated on a Hill very pleaſantly. The Walls are much gone to ruine, having but few Guns, and thoſe without Carriages. The Ruines are above three miles about the Caſtle. The Plain is very delightſome, abounding with Wine, Oyl, and all ſorts of Grain.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <head>TRAPOLIZZA, formerly called MEGALOPOLIS,</head>
               <p>Hath the Name of a City, tho' it be not ſo big as ſome Towns. It is now the chief place of all the (once Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous)
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96620:8"/>Province of <hi>Arcadia.</hi> The <hi>Turks</hi> call it <hi>Mora Orta,</hi> that is, the Center or Middle of the <hi>Morea.</hi> Here are very rich <hi>Turks,</hi> who have their Wealth in Land and Cattle; moſt being Graziers and Husbandmen. This is the only place which deſerves the Name of a Town in the whole Province. The Great <hi>Moske</hi> was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Heathen Temple. The Houſes are very mean: The <hi>Turks</hi> live moſt in their Farms, which they call Cheftlicks, not being in danger of Pyrats. The Province of <hi>Arcadia</hi> is all ſurrounded with Mountains, moſt of which are covered with Woods. Yearly they burn the Graſs and Bryers to clear the ground againſt the Spring, then very good Paſture grows up in its ſtead. There hath been many Villages, ſome have been Cities, but now the <hi>Albaneſes,</hi> (who are the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds, and three times the Number, as the <hi>Turks,</hi> and <hi>Greeks</hi> which are in theſe parts) live moſt in Tents, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving their Tents and Herds according to the ſeaſon of the Year. In the Summer time they are up in the Mountains, and in the Winter they are in the Woods by the Sea ſide, being more or leſs Tents together. There are a ſort of theſe <hi>Albaneſes</hi> which have a great Village called <hi>Syleman,</hi> as the Mountains have the ſame Name. Theſe <hi>Albaneſes</hi> have often Rebelled and kept themſelves up in the Mountains, doing much miſchief by Robbery. They were ſo ſtrong in the Year 1679, as the <hi>Baſsha</hi> went with 500 Men to reduce them by granting a General Pardon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <head>LEPANTO, formerly called NA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PACT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</head>
               <p>And now by the <hi>Turks Einabackti,</hi> ſtands on the <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mili</hi> ſhoar about three Miles within the Caſtles at the Entrance of that Gulph. It is ſcituated on the ſide of a high and ſteep Hill, having ſix Walls from the Water-ſide to the Caſtle, which croſs the Hill, all
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96620:8"/>which and the Caſtle are furrounded with a high Wall, which runs up at each ſide of the City. The Houſes ſtand ſcattering between theſe ſeveral Walls, but the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part are by the Sea-ſide. The Caſtle ſtands on the top of the Hill. It is kept in very good repair. There are about twenty very good Guns. The Port is almoſt Oval, having a very narrow Entrance. There is a Chain which paſſes from one ſide to the other. At each ſide of the Entrance are places for many Guns, tho' now they have not above three or four. The City is well Peopled being a Neſt of Pyrats. It yielded to the <hi>Turk</hi> in the Year 1499, after a long Siege before. The <hi>Turks</hi> having the Caſtles at the Entrance into the Gulph, the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> had no hopes of Relief, ſo were forced to yield themſelves up to their Mercy, who gave them free leave to depart. In the time of War with the <hi>Venetians</hi> the <hi>Briganteens</hi> of this place were a continual Plague to the People of <hi>Zant,</hi> and <hi>Ceffalonia.</hi> A Famous Corſare of this place called <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach Beigh,</hi> went with Eleven <hi>Briganteens</hi> and in the Night time Landed at <hi>Cherri,</hi> on the South part of the Iſland of <hi>Zant,</hi> taking away above 200 Slaves, and at Day break appeared before the Port of <hi>Zant</hi> with Colours flying, and firing his Guns, gave them notice of his Prize, almoſt as ſoon as they had the News by Land; ſo got ſafe to his Port with this great Succeſs. The day before was a ſolemn Feaſt kept at <hi>Cherri,</hi> and many People came from the City of <hi>Zant</hi> to pay their Devotions to the <hi>Panaija</hi> there. Since the Peace with the <hi>Venetians,</hi> they go upon the Coaſt of <hi>Apuglia,</hi> and take poor Countrey-men, bringing them to miſerable Slavery. The City of <hi>Lepanto</hi> hath the whole trade of the Gulph, here being the Cuſtomer who takes his Duties on all Boats that go in or out. The plains are very pleaſant, at each ſide of the City, with many Olive-trees, and Vine-yards. To the Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96620:9"/>of the City about a quarter of a Mile out of Town, there is a great Spring which guſheth out of a Rock at the Foot of a high Mountain; it divides into ſeveral Streams which makes ſome Iſlands, theſe Iſlands are moſt cut ſquare, which are covered by vaſt high Plane-trees, that ſtand very thick, and ſo, as at Noon-day it is ſhady all about the Spring. In the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time here are continually many <hi>Turks,</hi> bringing their Victuals with them, and tarry moſt part of the day. About Fifteen Miles from hence, upon the ſame ſide of the Gulph, ſtands a ſmall Village called <hi>Vitre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizza,</hi> near unto which Sir <hi>Giles Eaſtcourt</hi> was Buried, travelling in Company with Mr. <hi>Francis Vernon;</hi> and in his way towards Mount <hi>Parnaſſus,</hi> Sir <hi>Giles</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained in the Morning, but would not be perſwaded to tarry at <hi>Lepanto,</hi> hoping it would paſs: he called to his man to help him down, and in leſs then half an hour he Dyed, and was Buried with the aſſiſtance of <hi>Greek</hi> Prieſts, who live in <hi>Vitrenizza.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are two Caſtle at the Entrance of the Gulph of <hi>Lepanto:</hi> One is on the <hi>Morea</hi> ſhore, the other on <hi>Rumili;</hi> the Enterance between them is not above a Mile and a half, nor can any Ship paſs without danger of being ſunk, there being ſeveral Guns in each Caſtle which lye level with the Water. The Caſtles alſo ſland very low.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <head>NATALICO,</head>
               <p>Is a large Town ſtanding in a Bay, which hath lying before it, two Iſlands that keep off the main force of the Sea. From the Eaſtern part at the Entrance of the Bay up to the Town, is a <hi>Peſcaria</hi> or Fiſhery, it being very ſhallow, and the bottom muddy, with Weeds; but that part to the Northward of the Town is very deep. No Boats of any Burthen can come within a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96620:9"/>Mile of the Town, nor into that part above it. They have abundance of Monoxylos, or Cannows, which paſs through narrow Channels; with theſe they carry all their Goods to, and from the Town. The Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants are <hi>Greeks,</hi> no <hi>Turks</hi> living with them, except ſome of the Cuſtomers Officers, the Cuſtomer himſelf living at <hi>Mezzalnnzi,</hi> a place about ten Miles diſtant, upon the ſide of this Bay. Both theſe Towns are well Peopled: Neither of them have any Fortification; no Enemy can come by Water to annoy them. On the Eaſtermoſt Iſland is a ſmall Chappel called St. <hi>Soſti,</hi> againſt which Ships do Anchor when they come to load. Their Loading is brought from the Town to this Iſland with Monoxylos, from whence it is carried aboard in the Ships Boats.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THE Inhabitants of the <hi>Morea,</hi> are <hi>Turks, Greeks, Albaneſes</hi> and <hi>T'Zackonians.</hi> The <hi>Turks</hi> for the moſt part live in, or under the Command of Caſtles, and at their Farms in the Country (where they ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times are;) they have Towers built about Thirty Foot high, the Door of which is about ten Foot from the ground; againſt which a Wall with Stairs is built, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout five Foot from the Tower, to which Wall a Draw-bridge is let down from before the Door where they enter: 'tis every Night drawn up to ſecure them from Pirats; ſome have only a Ladder, which they take up into the Tower. There is a continual Watch in the Summer time, all along the Sea Coaſts. Of <hi>Turks'</hi> there are not above 30000 Inhabitants; the Chriſtians are three times as many. The <hi>Greeks</hi> have free Exerciſe of their Religion. Their Prieſts are very ignorant; ſcarce any underſtanding the old <hi>Greek;</hi> nor are they ſo Superſtitious in their worſhip to Pictures,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96620:10"/>as thoſe who live under the <hi>Venetians.</hi> They have ſeveral Monaſteries. Near unto <hi>Voſtiza</hi> is one, which is called, <hi>La Madona di Spiglia,</hi> it being at the ſide of a Mountain in a large Cave, where there is a Church, in which is the Picture of the Virgin <hi>MARY,</hi> which (they ſay) was brought hither from <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> by Angels at the time when the <hi>Turks</hi> took that City. There was another <hi>Madona</hi> near <hi>Miſithra,</hi> which did many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles; and every Year great numbers of <hi>Greeks</hi> flock'd from all parts to pay their Devotions to it. The <hi>Baſſha</hi> of the <hi>Morea</hi> having notice, went to ſee the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, telling the Prieſts he was deſirous to ſee ſome Miracle; they telling him it had done many, he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered one of his Men to bring him another Picture out of any Houſe, which being brought, he asked the Prieſts what difference there was betwixt thoſe two Pictures, they anſwered, that, that Picture which was in the Church was a moſt Sacred thing. But the <hi>Baſſha</hi> cauſed a Fire to be made, and both Pictures to be put into it, ſaying, he would Worſhip that which eſcaped the Fire; but both were burnt, and the <hi>Baſſha</hi> laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at their Superſtition, went his way. The Chriſtians live much better here than in <hi>Aſia.</hi> The vulgar <hi>Greek</hi> is the general Language, and there are few <hi>Turks</hi> but can ſpeak it. Every Town hath <hi>Greek</hi> Elders which they call <hi>Yerondo's.:</hi> Theſe appear upon all Publick Matters, and levy Taxes on the Towns-People, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably to their Abilities. The <hi>Albaneſes</hi> are of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church. They generally live not in Towns, yet have ſeveral Villages; one of which is very large, called <hi>Sylemen.</hi> It ſtands in the Mountains near the City of <hi>Arcadia,</hi> which Mountains have the ſame Name. They live moſt in Tents, being for the moſt part Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds. The <hi>T'Zackonians</hi> are moſt in Towns, they are a very poor People, ſerving as Porters, both Men and Women carrying very great Burthens. There are alſo a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96620:10"/>great many Jews, who for the moſt part are Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and Shop-keepers, living but poorly; the <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Merchants ſupplying moſt of the Country with all ſorts of Merchandizes, and chiefly from <hi>Venice.</hi> The <hi>Turks</hi> are very rich in their Cloathing here, their Veſts being moſt made with fine <hi>Venice</hi> Cloth.</p>
               <p>The Merchandizes of the <hi>Morea,</hi> or Product of the Land, are Olive-Oyl, Raw-Silk, Wax, Honey, Soap, Cordovan-skins, Sheep-skins, Butter, Cheeſe, Raiſons, Currans, Figgs, Wines, Wheat, Barly, Rye, Oates, dry'd Acorns (which the <hi>Venetians</hi> call <hi>Valania,</hi> and which are uſed in <hi>Italy</hi> for Tanning of Leather, as we uſe the Bark of the Tree,) Fuſtick Wood, and Pernicoke Seed, which Seed is for Dyeing of Scarlet. It grows on a Shurb-Oak-tree, riſing at the ſtemm of the Leaf, like a Bliſter, ſomething bigger than a Pea, out of which comes Duſt (or Powder) which being dry turns to ſmall Worms, which when quickned they kill with Wine. The Soyl of the Land is very good. They Plow with two Oxen, and without Wheels, nor are they at the pains to dung the Ground. They have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Weeds, and the Liquorice Root is very troubleſome being deep. They reap their Corn much in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as we do, but have no Barns, only Threſhing-floors, (which the <hi>Turks</hi> call <hi>Chirman.</hi>) They are on high ground, and open to the Winds. Here they tread it out with Horſes, which are made faſt to a Poſt, round which the Corn is put; the Horſes trampling upon it make great diſpatch: with the Wind they cleanſe it, and ſend it home to their Houſes; that which they intend to keep they put into great Earthen Jarrs, and Baskets made with ſlit Canes, which Baskets are dawb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over with wet Cow-dung, which being well dryed, not only keeps in the Corn, but alſo preſerves it cool. The <hi>Turks</hi> are uſually at theſe places with a Watch, well Armed (if near the Sea) all the time of the Corn
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96620:11"/>treading. They have great quantity of Graſs, but make no Hay, feeding their Horſes with chopt Straw and Barly; they Litter them with Horſe-dung, which being dryed in the Sun, and ſhaken, falls aſunder, and is very ſoft. In the Spring they feed them with green Barly, tying one of their hinder-leggs to a Stake, which they remove twice a day, keeping them to an allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. Beſides the Common Graſs, they have a ſort of Clover Graſs, which they give them Green, after their feeding on Barly, bringing it home to their Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. In <hi>Auguſt</hi> the common Graſs is uſually parcht and dry, which therefore they burn, and new ſoon ſprings up in its place.</p>
               <p>The Trees in the Woods are ſeveral ſorts of Oaks, Pine, Firr, wild Cheſnut and wild Pear.</p>
               <p>In their Gardens they have Orange, Lemon, Citron, Pomegranate, Apricock, Peach, Plum, and Cherry-Trees; Apples and Pears they have not many, nor are they ſo good as uſually they be with us; Cypreſs-trees and Wallnuts they are plenty. In the Plains near any Springs, are moſt ſtately Plane-trees, which are very ſhady. They have all ſorts of Garden Herbs as we have, and great quantity of Musk-melons, Water Melons, and ſeveral ſorts of Gourds.</p>
               <p>In the Month of <hi>December,</hi> they begin to make Oyl, continuing it till the beginning of <hi>March,</hi> or accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as the quantity of Olives is. <hi>February, March,</hi> and <hi>April,</hi> are for making Butter and Cheeſe, alſo for ſheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Sheep. <hi>May</hi> and <hi>June</hi> is the time for cutting their Corn. In <hi>June</hi> and <hi>July</hi> they are imployed in gathering Mulberry Leaves to feed their Silk-worms. <hi>Auguſt, September,</hi> and <hi>October,</hi> are for gathering and drying their Currans, Figgs, Raiſons, Valania, Perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coke Seed, and Tobacco; alſo for making their Wine and taking up their Honey and Wax.</p>
               <p>Their Oyl they put into great Earthen Jarrs, which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96620:11"/>are made of hard Clay, well baked in Furnaces, but not glazed, which therefore will not keep Water from ſoaking through them. Theſe Jarrs are ſent to <hi>Candy,</hi> and other places for Merchandize. To preſerve their Cheeſe they ſift Earth, mix it with Salt and Water, then with it Coat over the Cheeſe, which keeps it cool, but makes it very Salt. A great quantity of this Cheeſe is yearly carried to <hi>Venice:</hi> It ſerves the ordinary People, who ſometimes grate it upon their boyl'd Macaroons, and Rice, inſtead of <hi>Parmiſan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though the <hi>Turks</hi> drink no Wine, yet they take New Wine and boyl it up to a Syrrup (which they call <hi>Bec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mez,</hi> and we call <hi>Cute,</hi>) putting it into ſmall Jarrs, they drink it mingled with Water, for this they account to be no Wine. They call new Wine <hi>Shira,</hi> and old Wine <hi>Shirab.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their Buildings are moſt of Bricks made of Clay, and chopt Straw, and dryed in the Sun. The Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the Walls are of Stone, and Lime. Few Houſes are above two Story high; they are covered over with Pan Tiles. There are not many great Houſes in all the <hi>Morea,</hi> the beſt being at <hi>Napoli, Miſitha,</hi> and <hi>Corinth:</hi> Not above three deſerve the Name of <hi>Seraglios</hi> (as they call Palaces.) Fleſh and Fowl is plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful, but Fiſh is ſcarce. The Air is very temperate; there is ſeldome any Rain from <hi>April</hi> to <hi>Auguſt.</hi> The Winter is alſo very moderate, and laſteth not above two Months any thing Cold: There is ſeldome any Snow in the Plains</p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <pb facs="tcp:96620:12"/>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:96620:12"/>
               <head>A <hi>Deſcription</hi> of the <hi>CITY</hi> of ATHENS.</head>
               <p>IT is the Head City in the Province of <hi>Attica,</hi> and was once the greateſt Miſtreſs of Learning in all <hi>Europe.</hi> The Plain is about Sixteen Miles Long, and Five Broad, being ſurrounded with Mountains, all but towards the South, where it is waſhed by the <hi>Egean</hi> Sea. The Olive-trees ſtand ſo thick to the Weſt of the City that they ſeem to be a Wood, reaching Six Miles in Length, and Two in Breadth. Whilſt I was there, a <hi>Tahrirge</hi> (or Surveyor) came down from <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to Survey the Place; he found above Fifty Thouſand Olive-trees in this Plain, and other places about the City. There are ſeveral ſmall Villages, where are very pleaſant Gardens, which afford all ſort of Fruit and Saleting, having Walks round them covered with Vines, of which there are two ſorts; the one is in the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Language called <hi>Barmak <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zumi,</hi> a long White Grape; the other <hi>Hevengh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zumi,</hi> a round Red Grape, both which growing in very large Bunches. Of the latter Mr. <hi>Vernon</hi> weighed one Bunch which was near Four Oaks (about Ten Pound <hi>Engliſh.</hi>) Theſe Red Grapes are not ripe till <hi>September,</hi> then they cut them off, and hang them up in their Houſes for Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtore. Neither of theſe Two ſorts grow in Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards. The Vine-yards are planted moſt betwixt the City, and the Sea. The City is now not above Three Miles about: Being Four Miles from <hi>Porto Lion,</hi> (which formerly was call <hi>Pirea</hi>) having a Caſtle to the South. The Houſes are better built here than in any part of the <hi>Morea,</hi> moſt having little Courts, with high Walls,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96620:13"/>in which are Arches with Marble Pillars; few Houſes above Two Story high: They alſo patcht up with the Ruines of old Palaces, and in moſt Walls are abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of old Inſcriptions. The Governors are in the ſame manner as they be in other Cities under the <hi>Turks.</hi> The <hi>Greeks</hi> live much better here than in any other part of <hi>Turky,</hi> (<hi>Scio</hi> excepted) being a ſmall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth amongſt themſelves. They chooſe eight Magiſtrates, who adjuſt all differences, and appear in all Publick Matters. Their Protector (at the Port) is the Grand Seigniors Chief Eunuch, who hath the diſpoſing of that Government. The City is not Walled about, but has Gates at the Streets end, which every Night are ſhut, to keep out Privateers, who often Land and do much miſchief. Here is an Arch-Biſhop whoſe Houſe ſtands to the South Weſt of the Town, near unto the Mount <hi>Ariopagus:</hi> He lives in great eſteem amongſt them. Below his Palace towards the North, ſtands intire the Temple of <hi>Theſeus,</hi> which is a fair and large Building, all of White Marble, having a Portico about it with Pillars. The Temple is Seventy Three Foot long, and Twenty Six in Breadth: The Length of the Portico (which goes round it,) is One Hundred Twenty Three Foot: It is now a <hi>Greek</hi> Church, and Dedicated to St. <hi>George.</hi> To the South Eaſt part of the Caſtle are Seventeen Marble Pillars, being the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of One Hundred and Twenty, on which the Emperor <hi>Adrian</hi> had his Palace: And upon ſome of the Pillars which ſtand towards the Eaſt, is to be ſeen part of the Foundation. Theſe Pillars are of a pure White Marble, with blewiſh Waves, Schollop-work, being Fifty Foot in heighth, and Nineteen and a half round. The Ground is very even about them, which they ſay was formerly Paved with Marble. Cloſe to theſe Pillars Eaſtward, is a ſquare Piece of Ground, which is Walled in with a low Wall, being Green: It is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96620:13"/>kept very ſmooth and free of Stones; at the South End cloſe to the Wall, is a place (raiſed with Two Steps) about Two Foot high, almoſt in Form of a Throne. In the time of their <hi>Byram,</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> come to this place, where their Emam or Prieſt (ſitting on the raiſed place) Preacheth to them, ſhewing them the Vanity of the World, the Greatneſs of their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, and the Valour of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Forces, conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with a Prayer for the Grand Seignior, which is anſwered with Three Shouts from the Auditors, with a loud Voice crying, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Caſtle ſtands on a Rock, which is high and ſteep, having but one way up, and three Gates to paſs through into the Body of it: The Walls are much out of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair. The Scituation makes it ſtrong. This Caſtle ſtood almoſt in the middle of Old <hi>Athens:</hi> The Place moſt worth Obſervation in it, is the Temple of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerva,</hi> which remains entire, being eſteemed (by all who have ſeen it) to be one of the Moſt Glorious Buildings in <hi>Europe.</hi> It is all pure White Marble: The Length of the Body of the Temple is One Hundred Sixty Eight <hi>Engliſh</hi> Feet, and the Breadth Seventy One: There are Seventeen Pillars at each Side, and Eight at the Front: The Circuit of the Pillars are Nineteen Foot and a Half: The Length of the whole Temple Two Hundred and Thirty Feet. The Temple is very dark, having only ſome Lights to the Eaſtward. The <hi>Greeks</hi> did Conſecrate, and Dedicated it to the Bleſſed Virgin. Since that, the <hi>Turks</hi> have perverted it with their Worſhip. The <hi>Turks</hi> have White-waſh'd the Inſide, notwithſtanding it is all of pure Marble. In and about <hi>Athens,</hi> are Two Hundred <hi>Greek</hi> Churches, (moſt of which have been Temples) but not one quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of them are now uſed. In the Plain and on moſt of the Hills, there are many ſmall Chappels. The Ruines are above Six Miles about, of which the Reader
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96620:14"/>may have full ſatisfaction by reading the Travels of Sir <hi>George Wheeler,</hi> who hath given a large and true Account of this City. Some Geographers call it <hi>Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines,</hi> which name was never known to the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants; the <hi>Turks</hi> call it <hi>Atinna,</hi> and the <hi>Greeks Athine.</hi> The Air is very good. The Soyl rich. It hath a River to the South, cloſe by the Ruines of <hi>Adrians</hi> Palace, called <hi>Illiſus</hi> or <hi>Calleroy;</hi> which is almoſt choaked up, and in Summer is dry. The Harbour of <hi>Porto Lione</hi> is very ſecure from the danger of any Wind, but there is no Fortification, ſo that it is frequented by Pyrats. In all the Villages and Country about <hi>Athens,</hi> the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants are moſt <hi>Albaneſes;</hi> and they are here more populous than in the <hi>Morea.</hi> It affords the ſame Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities: and all Proviſion is as reaſonable, but their Wines in general are not ſo good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <head>The Iſland of <hi>ZANT,</hi> formerly called <hi>ZACYNTH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Is under the <hi>Venetians,</hi> lying about 15 miles from the South Weſt point of the <hi>Morea.</hi> The Weſt part is all Mountains, and to the North Eaſt is another Mountain (called <hi>Scopo</hi>) between which it is very low land, ſo as from the Southward at Sea it appears to be two Iſlands. The chief Road hath the name of the Iſland. The Town ſtretcheth it ſelf above a mile along that Bay; it is well built, with Free-ſtone, but the Houſes are low, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Earth-quakes, which are very frequent. To the Weſt, over the Town, ſtands the Caſtle, on a high and ſteep Hill, and is a ſmall City in it ſelf: The Wall is above a mile about. The Governour is a Noble-man of <hi>Venice:</hi> There is an <hi>Italian</hi> Biſhop, and three <hi>Italian</hi> Churches: But the <hi>Greeks</hi> (who are the chief Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants (have a <hi>Proto Papa,</hi> and all Feſtivals are obſerved ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the old ſtile. In the Iſland is above 30 Villages, and more than 60000 Souls. The Corn which grows
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96620:14"/>here will not ſuffice above three months; but in time of Peace with the <hi>Turks,</hi> they are well ſupplied from the <hi>Morea,</hi> and in time of War Corn is brought from <hi>Apuglia,</hi> and other parts in the Gulph of <hi>Venice.</hi> One year with another it produceth near 10000 Tun of Wine, 200 Tun of Oyl, and 2000 Tun of Currants; and may be compared, for pleaſantneſs and richneſs, with any Iſland (of its bigneſs) in the World. The Currants grow on Vines, and ſpread themſelves on the ground like other Grapes: In <hi>July</hi> they gather them, and ſpread them on a very ſmooth part of ground, where they lye until they are well dry'd, then they fall off from the Stalks; ſo are carry'd and put into Ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, where they are kept till the Merchants buy them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <head>
                  <hi>STRAFADA</hi> Iſlands.</head>
               <p>They are two ſmall Iſlands which lye about 20 miles from <hi>Zant,</hi> and 30 from the <hi>Morea.</hi> On the bigger is a Monaſtery well built, which hath a high Tower: There is about 40 Prieſts of the Order of St. <hi>Baſil.</hi> They work the ground, and have all ſorts of Fruits and Sallating; but their ſupply of Bread, Oyl and Wine, is brought them from <hi>Zant,</hi> where they have poſſeſſions. They never eat Fleſh. When any Pyrats come to moleſt them, they ſhut themſelves up in the Tower of the Monaſtery. There is no Harbour for Ships, ſo as ſeldom any come to trouble them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <head>
                  <hi>PRODINO</hi> and <hi>SAPIENZA</hi> Iſlands</head>
               <p>Are not Inhabited, but afford ſecure Harbours for Shipping, eſpecially the latter, where the <hi>Venetians</hi> often lye, to look out for Pyrats of <hi>Barbary,</hi> who uſe to cruiſe about <hi>Navareene,</hi> and <hi>Modon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="location">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:96620:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SERIGO,</hi> formerly called <hi>CYTHERA,</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Is under the <hi>Venetians,</hi> and withſtood the <hi>Turks</hi> Forces which Landed there ſeveral times; the Inhabitants (who are <hi>Greeks</hi>) retired to the Caſtle, which is ſtrong, yet the <hi>Turks</hi> might have taken it, but thought it not worth the loſs of his men, there being no good Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for Shipping; nor is the Land fruitful, being moſt Stony. The Governour is a Noble-man of <hi>Venice.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:96620:15"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
